- Versus Quest is more developer-driven
called VR or XR device.
So it's a little bit different.
One is more for user center,
the other one is more for technology terminology.
So yeah.
I think my breath is very loud.
I'm trying to, (laughs)
- Give it the little tilt.
Yeah, yeah, yeah. There you go.
- Yeah. Yeah.
- I mean, it's not like I haven't performed before.
It's not my first rodeo.
- Cool. - Yeah.
One minute and we'll be starting,
- Sorry.
- Today we won't have any visual presentation,
but more of a Q and A with the XR industry leader.
Yeah, so.
Okay.
So time's up.
So we are good?
Good. Okay, cool.
So yeah, thank you so much for joining our panel.
My name is Dominique Wu.
Currently, I'm the adjunct professor for Kenyatta College.
Woo. (audience cheering)
Yeah, a little bit of of advertising.
Kenyatta College is the most forward thinking college,
community college. (audience laughing)
I know everybody was very happy.
Yeah, and Menlo Park Studio, right,
XR Studio led by Hila is demonstrating
a really amazing XR apprenticeship.
Definitely, you know, check out Kenyatta College.
Yeah. Okay.
So a little bit of ads.
Okay.
So today's, yeah,
and besides adjunct professor at Kenyatta College,
I'm teaching coding for designers and artists using AI
to assisting students doing vibe coding
and also all the game prop creation.
And also I'm serving as one of the AI fellows
for the Chancellor's Office.
(audience applauding) Yay. Thank you.
Okay, so today's topic is called,
The Rise of Synthetic AI Companions.
So yeah, and it was my honor to invite
a lot of my industry friends, XR leaders.
So today they are the shining star
and also they are the speakers.
And they will,
we will have a lot of like inspiring conversations
between our panel speakers.
Yeah, so maybe we can start with introduction.
So we will start with who you are, what do you do,
and what inspire you to be here today.
Maybe that's start with Chris.
- Thank you, Dominique.
And hello, everyone.
So happy to be here with you today.
And certainly,
hope you have this joined this Futures Summit.
My name's Christopher Lafayette,
Emergent Technologist Humanitarian,
founder of several different ventures
here in Silicon Valley and abroad.
And work with Nvidia on several different ventures
and Microsoft as well in AI.
I have been in this space as emergent technologist
studying over 270 technologies.
For me, the inspiration for being here is,
I am a community college dropout
and I don't recommend it for everyone.
And I left community college to move
to move to Silicon Valley living outta the seat of my car.
And I never thought that I'd be afforded
the opportunities I've had.
I traveled the world and speaking at,
and lecturing in different universities around the world
and the Valley as well
and having a really incredible sense on
where we meet at the intersection
of emerging technologies and humanity first considerations
of education and community development
and safety and privacy and wellness and ethics
and so much more and trust worthy AI
along with the technology that we're adopting now,
it's never been more important than ever.
And I am an advocate for students to live
on a bifurcated path when it comes to the career path,
but also entrepreneurial ship.
We're heading into a time of a trajectory of the AI frontier
where we find ourselves now
where we're going under the most
consequential disruptive phase of AI
and hyper scale that we've ever known.
We'll never know more of a time like this.
And when it comes to the human capacity of innovation,
this is the last front of humans, of the nuclear,
of the corpus of more human innovation that we'll ever know.
At some point within a eight to nine month trajectory,
not a year, eight to nine months, we will be competing
with the machine species and humans that are with machines,
agentic systems that will remain
and will continue to be more autonomous than ever.
I advocate for not slowing down,
but for staying ahead of machine innovation
because machines will never be able
to supersede the human code.
And that is something that we are afforded always
and we must as educators of teaching this technology
for what's next is staying ahead of the wave.
I advocate for autonomy.
I know the hands went up when it comes to adopting ChatGPT,
Claude, Cursor and a number of different models.
We're studying over 1,800,000 models right now.
And I advocate that everyone in education,
every college, every campus in the world should develop
and own their own autonomous systems when it comes to AI
because I would not want to be dependent
on the future of education based on Sam Altman's intuition.
Thank you. (audience applauding)
- Good night, everyone. (audience laughing)
- Good luck, Mike.
- I wanted to go back to the title,
like The Rise of Synthetic AI.
I mean, sounds like a "Transformers" movie title.
I'm a little nervous here.
I'm Mike.
I'm a experienced design technologist.
I'm building the WIZO,
it's the world's first AI adventure mentor.
So I'm just essentially trying
to gamify the person's journey by, you know,
seeking some good advice hopefully.
And my reason for being here is,
I was once one of your students,
I went through a lot of colleges, actually.
I moved a lot.
So my first community college experience was,
I went to Evergreen Valley College in San Jose City College
at the same time, which was driving back and forth.
And then I moved to Santa Clara
and I went to Mission College for half a year,
just right across.
And then I moved to Boise, Idaho,
and I was like, I didn't finish my associates.
So I wrapped it up there at CWI and then Boise State
and then came back here and got my master's
at San Jose State this year.
So all over the place. Yeah. (audience applauding)
And then, let's see, am I supposed to match his time
or is it your turn?
- It's all good.
- You do whatever you need to do then Mike.
Sounds like you got the full community
college experience though.
That sounds pretty cool.
- Not too much.
- Hi, I'm Robin Moulder,
CEO 3lb XR and 3lb games.
So we build cutting edge games in 3lb.
In the 3lb game side,
it's cutting edge spatial computing, you know,
XR, immersive technologies with AI of course
we also have taken our tools,
everything we've learned since 2016
of just building all these amazing immersive experiences,
and we've gone the market with our tool sets
so that everybody can build these experiences
without having to know all of the things that we know,
object oriented design,
kind of like imagine what you wanna do,
type it into our AI assist and helper
and then it helps you build your experience,
facial computing in AI, immersive technology,
whatever you wanna call it these days.
It's that broader umbrella of anything
that makes something spatial.
We also work colleges and university.
So we've been doing a lot of,
I spoke at Kanata.
Thank you very much, Dominique.
That was super fun. - Yeah.
- So I've been running around doing a lot of workshops
to get students up to speed on our tool set because
this is a great place where they're gonna get jobs.
And I find that this community college,
everything that we're saying here,
everything that we heard in the keynote is so important
to get actual jobs for students.
'Cause if they don't see the path to getting a job
by coming to your class or coming to your college,
there will be no more colleges.
They'll all learned online.
So I love the focus of this camp,
that this whole conference
and that it's about helping you get the tools that you need
to be successful with your students,
helping to draw in the students
with the right type of content.
Love it, and very excited about this next two days.
- Cool. Yeah.
So our speakers had a lot of experience,
also the pioneer for XR emerging spatial AI expertise.
So, okay.
So let's go back to our first question.
What's AI companion exactly,
or according to your opinion, what's AI companion?
- I would say on a high level that one of the things that
I want us all to admonish
and to really kind of lean in on this
on a very candid level is that
the AI that we're interacting with tonight,
that we're texting in this language foundational models
and generated pre-trained transformers is so rudimentary
and so minimal compared to what it will be not next year
but even December.
I would submit to you that the AI
that we're interacting with today is nothing compared
to what we'll see this time next year.
Not even with phraseology as SAGI
and theory of mind and and more,
but we have to understand the intent
was never for us to sit around and to tap on these devices.
But the intent was for us to be able to walk
and to be able to live inside one of these devices.
The intent is not to be able to communicate
with what we'll call parametric or Concatenative synthesis,
meaning the speech of a model
or the computer vision of a model that can see you
and it can be seen by you,
and at the same time, not just see you,
but be able to understand your disposition.
And this is what we call theory of mind.
And at some point it will look at its own self
and believe that it has a disposition.
And so we call it self-aware that
what we're heading into is
hyper-realistic immersive simulation
or realtime augmented projection that you'll come home
and have supper with Siri face-to-face,
that the AI that you're interacting with today,
it's not just phonetic language that's post inference,
but it's going to have embodiment, caricature, disposition.
It's gonna be almost anthropomorphized.
It will have head cavity, chest cavity,
lower abdominal cavity.
You can imagine seeing that.
And it's going to be so not uncanny,
but it will not be discernible
to your human sensors or your human factors.
This is perceptual science, that when you're interacting
with these machines, if you will,
they'll have extended long chain of thought reasoning,
memory process and it will have conversations
and remember things better than what you did.
It will remember what you had for dinner last night,
two years from now.
It will be able to recite and understand
your whole body autonomy.
It will be able to understand things about you
that you forgot you even said it to it,
to be able to diagnose and assess
to molecular structure on the protein structure.
Right now I'm looking at,
I speak in front of many audiences,
advise the White House and more different organizations,
private and public sector,
but what I'm looking at right now is the frontline workers
to education to what's next in the frontier.
It may not seem like that
because maybe the dollars to cents doesn't spell that out,
but I assure you that right now there are some of you
in this room, I know what I'm talking about,
that are hesitant
and apathetic or apprehensive to adopting this technology
because this technology is an apex predator,
AI is an apex predator.
It will take your job, it will disrupt.
But as I asked an audience five years ago
in Florence, Italy,
what happens when the technology becomes
more advanced than the technology is?
What happens when the Vibe code says to the Vibe coder,
"I don't need you anymore?"
At some point, - Going to Cabo.
- We must realize that we must move
at an accelerating fashion to not only stay up with AI,
but to be able to compete and accelerate past it.
This is not a fantastic ideology.
This is enshrouded and embedded in truth.
So a companion is somebody
that will be evergreen present with you.
Your companion will be that one sitting
in the classroom with you,
communicating and allowing the teacher, the educator,
for the educator to communicate with the students more,
remove and eliminate the redundancy
of having to do the remedial tasks that are often driven
towards apathy in a teacher's life and education.
Removing that out of the way,
giving more time for the intimate relationship
that's needed between the student and the teacher,
and at the same time, as I close,
that they also will have their AI assisted companions.
And your companion, AI assistant,
will communicate with their companions.
This is cross-cultural communication,
intercultural development.
And it will know how to communicate with this companion.
'cause its companion knows how to communicate it
with them better than you will.
And it will be able to assimilate and to be able to assess.
This is where we're headed,
and we must have the frame of mind
to move fast and to move swift
because at some point within about nine to 10 months,
hold me to it, you will not have the opportunity
to take advantage of the time that you have now.
The half-life is unforgiving.
This is the time and this is why we have these sessions.
'cause we'll have a different conversation next year
and I will be interacting with more machines on your behalf.
You can take that to the bank. The warning has gone out.
We're here at Ground Zero. The game is changing.
Right now,
once these energy platforms are built and developed,
Hyperion, Colossus 1 and 2, Colossus is done.
Stargate, the biggest financial investments
we've ever seen in AI,
and any technology we've ever known
has happened in the first six months of this year
and we're not going back.
Why are they building so much power infrastructure?
Physical AI companions, agentic systems,
the high mind is here upon us.
It's the frontline workers, the educators
who are the heroes of the day.
And I'm in your favor and I advocate for you.
(audience applauding)
- Michael. (audience laughing)
Mike, next one.
After this very big vision, your turn.
What's AI companion according to your thought?
- Yeah.
Well, if an AI remembers what I ate two,
- Oh. What happened?
What happened? You broke the mic, (speaks faintly)
- Oh wow.
There's a 75% chance that it was leftover pizza
and 25% chance it wasn't leftover that night.
(audience laughing) No.
(Robin speaks faintly)
- Yeah.
Yeah, I mean an AI companion, it's a, you know,
it's a digital partner.
Someone you can talk to all day long or all you know,
when don't want to, you know,
how many of you do not like getting texts at 11:00 PM,
or what time did you,
were you texting this morning, Dominique?
5:00 AM? - Oh 5:00.
- I wake up at 4:00. I wake up at 4:00.
- But no, I mean like, you know,
it's, you know,
it's beyond just, you know, having a mentor.
But it's there to, you know,
to be there when someone isn't,
and that's really important for some people
or a lot of people.
- These are all really great comments
and to me it's the,
it is the communication layer for you
with literally everybody else.
Those of us on the neurodiversity scale,
which is literally everybody,
if whatever you are missing,
whatever it is that you have trouble
communicating with person or with the computer,
this is a way for you to show up,
and this is a way for you to have those layers.
I personally, do not like to read long texts,
long, big, long emails
that sometimes people like to write me.
What a wonderful thing it is that I could just turn around
and like grab that and shove it over there.
What is also really great is when I just talk the ChatGPT,
I'll be cooking dinner or something
and I'm just having these conversations
about a thing that I would normally
have just been thinking about
and then rushing to my computer to type
and instead now I'm just having a conversation about it
while I'm going about my business
and just doing whatever I need to do.
This gives me this opportunity
to not worry about losing a thought
or losing a really cool phrase.
So having that contextual memory
is so important to your day-to-day life.
When it comes to, you know,
the ways that we get an education,
I can see this being a much more inviting for students
to come in because they'll be less afraid.
They will know that they have the support they need.
It's everything.
It's spatially somebody representing, you know,
to Christopher's comments there.
There's a lot to unpack in all of that.
If you think about a student who's struggling
and maybe sure the chatbot
can speak in their language, that's easy.
Great. What else can they do for you?
Can that chat bot actually notice
that you're a little sick today
and then that chat bot turn around
and talk to your advisor chatbot
and say, "Hmm, actually maybe you should cut them
some slack on this assignment
because they're actually sick."
There's a lot that you can do with all of this technology.
And a lot of it see you sitting down
identifying what are these gaps in,
in what's causing you the most pain,
really that's what it gets down to.
And that's what I've done with myself
and my business as I look for those maximum pain points
and then start to identify how can we use AI there
and slot it into the process.
So the chat bot itself
can kind of be whatever you need it to be.
It's kind of a lofty term.
So if it uses vision, that's great,
if it's just using voice and text, that's great too.
Eventually, for sure things are gonna pop up
in your spatial computing headset or like glasses
and then be sitting there having a conversation with you
or looking over your shoulder and saying,
"You know, actually you were supposed to put
screw two in first before screw four just so you know."
Whatever that support system that needs to be,
it's a very powerful tool
and it's just gonna get better from here.
- Yeah.
Have any of you saw the demo or the TEDTalk
for Android XR announcement?
Raise your hand. Okay.
Our people, Jason, a founder of Flow Immersive, okay.
So let me give you a little bit description of what I saw.
The demo is that people wear the glass like a Robin's glass,
like a normal glass.
And then the girl was like,
oh doing this, doing that,
and later on just said wear the glass
and later on just say, "Hey Google."
I don't know what's the name.
For Meta it's "Hey Meta."
But Google has, its its own, you know, calling.
Just say, "Hey Google, where's my key?"
You know, I find out this is a wonderful functions for me
'cause I always couldn't find my key
every time when I go out, right?
So you see like this companion is embedded
in your wearable, in your glass, right?
And it understand you.
It knows every movement and you call it when you need
and you don't even need a phone
'cause sometimes phone was lost.
But when you wear the glass or wearable,
it's pretty much very close to you.
So you see like,
and also the, when the girl do the demonstration,
she read a book and she read something
because the camera will read what you read
and you can see the girl just say,
"Hey, explain this to me, I don't understand."
And the Google Smart Glass or Android XR smart glass
will tell you exactly or like according to, you know,
Gemini, like a large language model and explain
to you what this book means.
So you see like in Meta Connect,
I saw one of my close friends post like rumor has said that
they are going to release the SDK Meta Connect,
which is next week, the SDK for RayBan.
What does that mean?
When you see people wear normal glass like a Robin,
maybe that's a camera, maybe it's a recording, right?
Yeah.
Maybe next year, Robin, you know, we need to be,
- Oh yeah, I'm lining,
oh we we'll be at Meta Connect
and I'll be like, - Yeah.
Yeah, two of us will be, - Take my money.
- Yeah.
And you know, have any of you here heard of Orion?
Alaa?
Jason?
Okay, Orion.
Orion was claimed to be, according to Mark Zuckerberg,
one of the most advanced AR glass, AR AI glass.
And right now they are going to release one eye,
like more like for researcher for AR AI.
But I mean, in the future, whatever you see,
for example, right now I have
like a small cheat sheet right here,
but in the future I might be able
to display on my smart glass.
So this is how you student cheat.
Right now you're afraid of them to screenshot
or type into ChatGPT in the future everything will display,
all the answer will be in front of their eyes.
How can you prevent the cheat, right?
So this will be,
- Take off your glasses before you walk in the classroom.
(audience laughing)
- Yeah.
Everybody has to be naked, right? Yeah.
We don't trust you, right?
You cannot wear anything.
Okay. So yeah.
So the next question will be, how can student and teachers
utilize AI companions for education?
(audience chattering)
- It's a heck of a time
to talk about naked audience people
and I'm trying not to look at the audience.
It's like that just doesn't work well.
Can you ask the question again please?
I can't get to, - Okay. Sorry.
When I say naked, everybody start having an image of it, so.
(audience laughing)
So the question, let me read it over.
How can students and teachers utilize AI companions?
- I think it first starts with identifying the needs
and the assessing what it is
that the students are looking to achieve.
But moreover to addressing the needs of the
teachers when it comes to the curricula.
You know, I look at today's AI
that's moving at such an accelerated pace
and it's moving at ludicrous speed and as it should
because we are in a global AI arms competition.
But that's a whole different narrative.
But when I look at the idea
of intersecting a companion into a classroom,
a classroom should be a place
of concentric circles that are safe.
And it also should be an environment that is from the onset,
encircled and enshrouded in trust.
And one of the things that we're doing in London
in working in concert with Switzerland is,
with our platform, just verified
and it's not a shameless plug because the work gets hard
but it's to look at how do we build a trust layer
when it comes to interacting with any of these models.
You mentioned Mark Zuckerberg and Orion
and all the other glasses of spectacles.
I see Jason there that deals in data and AR glasses.
I don't trust almost any AR glasses
'cause I don't even trust the devices,
majority of what it is that I interact with ecologically
within these systems.
And that's a really big problem.
And this is why I advocate,
and this is really important when I'm about to say,
and along with everything else that's being said,
is that educators and platforms,
we need to minimize and reduce,
not in the sake of protesting against
big corporate and big technology,
but you don't wanna find yourself vendor locked
in any of these models right now
because the turn that they take is the investment
that you make and you are buying it
to their decision making.
Move for autonomy, move for owning your own systems.
That's the first thing is,
what are we gonna take with our inherent data
that's according to the system that we operate within now.
Within this system, you would be surprised
how much data is yield every day from your environment
taking to the data that already exists, right,
I see some people shaking their head,
taking the data that already exists then the DNA data
that's contribute within your environment.
Every single time on prem, within an environment,
every time someone uses a device,
every time someone submits work,
every time someone submits a thesis,
every time someone introduces themselves to your world,
they are contributing to the overall system
of what we call in some ways
these human characteristics that are permeated
in and throughout technological ecosystems.
This is ecoculture.
That ecoculture in this polycultural setup has data.
And when we talk about data,
what you do with that is you take that,
translate that into a data stack and compile that,
and what you're really doing is you're extracting
cultural IP and you're taking sovereign AI.
This is why Nvidia just reached the scale, the top,
this is why they're the number one company in the world,
is because private sector understands that
we need to own our own systems.
They already made the calamity.
I've advised Meta, Warner Brothers and more,
and I can tell you and I can't tell you,
but I can tell you that some have made,
some companies have made the egregious era
of adopting these technologies that Sam Altman,
I have nothing against Sam, I don't even know him,
that's peddling these models and saying
this is the definitive way to go.
I think it's the lazy way to go.
I think for you to own your own systems,
we've never had this much democratized access before ever,
and it's affordable and compute,
but for you to own your own system
makes a more trustworthy system.
You know where the data comes from natively, inherently,
and you're able to work with that.
There's open source models that you can change
when it comes to fine tuning and more that you can control.
So it's not just, let's go and purchase an AI companion
and you have no idea the half life
of what will happen with that.
You don't know what's happening with your data.
Data as precious. It's the lifeblood of AI.
But moreover, what is it that these models are teaching?
These students, these young people
are becoming more dependent on AI
than ever before and technology.
I look around the room, most of us,
I'm not trying to point anyone out,
most of us are a little bit more mature in life.
We know what it is. - Respectful.
- We know what that hard work life is.
But these students are saying, "Let my model do it.
Let my AI do it. Let my AI think for me."
We need to come to where they're at,
we need to bring them into the process
of developing their own autonomous systems.
I'm building 16 models now.
Don't build large language foundational models.
Build small models, vertical out.
They'll save you a lot of time and money
with the GPUs that you can be able to gain.
Get into the habit of building out your own systems.
I said this to educators across the world in 2023.
I did more talks than I care to give.
When I told educators did they do it
and somebody asked me, "Admin,"
and this is a Cal Poly, he said,
"Well, where do we need to spend our money?"
My answer, "Don't spend your money.
Go back to your campuses.
Start to be able to curate your data,
find out how much you have.
Take your data, then once you have a decision
on how much data that you actually have, quantify that,
then go about the process
of interacting with these platforms
that give you the necessary tools to build your own."
This is the way to go.
Then your companion will natively,
intimately be based on your ecoculture.
That is what you want.
I promise you that's the way to go.
Anywhere else that you go with,
if you're gonna go with that,
build a modular constellation that allows you to build
with a number of different models at any given time.
Make sure they're filtered through a trust layer
and make sure they're filtered through a ethical layer
so you're not just taking their word for it
because of the safety, but these people,
they're depending on you to guide them
towards what's the better model to be able to use
and their lives are gonna be based on the information
that's deployed and distributed
from these models that you're going to use.
Never marry up the one model, keep it horizontal,
have an assortment, run it through a filter,
but ultimately build your own sovereignty.
This is important.
Lastly, I'll say this, I will be done with it.
I'm an advocate for women leadership in this world.
I have one of the biggest platforms in the world
for women's admins called Super Hero Engine.
SHE's somewhere over,
250 women are speaking at this event in January.
That's not a plug, this is real.
I'm also an advocate for men's health and women's health.
My bigger concern is that these models
are primarily developed in a monocultural fashion.
There's not enough people in the room,
whether it's dealing with communities of color, women
and men that are building and contributing
their cultural IP to these models.
We are quite literally using the extension of reality
of unlimited class of people in this world
and we're making whole entire business decisions on it.
So not to pick on men, I think that's important as well.
But I also think it's equally important to have women
and to be able to innovate.
I need my nieces to know they could be
anything they want to be in technology.
So when you're gonna build out these models,
if you take this route, make sure that everyone has a seat
that has a desire to innovate and to be able to build.
Accessibility is key at hand to make sure that
everyone can contribute their culture
and not just unlimited batch.
I don't want the models that I use
to be completely built by men
and I don't think you do either.
(audience applauding)
- So when you talk about building systems,
I agree with that too.
You know, open source models are, you know,
getting as good as some of those frontier models.
But there is always like a cost, right?
There's still a cost of processing storage, data storage.
So as a professor,
and plus there's a huge learning curve still in that case.
So that is the way we all should be thinking,
building our own systems where the your data,
your lessons, your plans are secure
and the student's data is secure, right?
It's not going out into a data farm somewhere else.
So here at WIZO, like we are in beta phases,
so we're just using GPT 5 Nano,
that's going to GPT 5's database.
If I can get GPT OSS, which is open source,
be able to, when you install my app,
you are installing the LLM on your phone,
then the data doesn't go anywhere.
So that's really good when you're building maybe
classroom applications, that would be the way to go.
But for now, the best way to use an AI companion
in the classroom, both faculty and students,
the faculty, you can be doing planning lessons,
you can kind of help you do some of the
more tedious tasks of teaching
while you can focus on exploring on new things.
Students are gonna be using it at home for,
to help them study, as a tutor,
to prepare for interviews for the real world.
And so that's gonna be integrated.
So your a faculty's role can be,
you are the anchor in the classroom.
You're there to kind of have a blended class of
human teaching and AI companion.
So your role is more important than ever
to just be that anchor for the students,
be the anchor, again, anchor of trust.
So that does include understanding, you know,
diving into what is,
what are these LLMs doing out there in the real world
to our students, to our ourselves?
And then how to reign that into the classroom
and making sure that there is, you know,
checks and balances?
And that's your role there too is to verify sources.
And this stuff that's way before AI,
I mean we always talked about,
in fact, before LMS were out in public
about three years ago,
I remember being in the classroom
and we were trying to talk about
how can we trust Google search or any kind of search.
So that was really a low level artificial
intelligence at the time.
There was a lot of debate in the classroom
'cause that's hard, that's hard to manage.
At the end of the day, it is your peers
and your colleagues that can kind
of help verify those systems.
So yeah, using it to build your plans,
build your agendas in the classroom,
but also being in control of, you know,
what sources are truthful,
most truthful at least, right,
and then how to kind of guide the students
who are gonna be using it regardless
to make sure that they're using it within, you know,
the effort that you put forth into that classroom.
- So how many of you are overworked currently?
Yeah, we go. There we go.
This is what I see.
This is your opportunity to sit back and identify
what do you not want to do at your job?
Like what did you sign up to do?
It wasn't this right?
It wasn't what you're doing right now.
And as a person who's built so many
workforce development type apps in spatial computing
and you know, sometimes leveraging AI
and sometimes not, just depends on what it was.
It just could be basic instructional design,
it is always the goal to both satisfy
how is it gonna help the students the most as well
as lighten your load, the work that you need to do.
So we always try to unpack those areas of,
hmm, it's something that everybody keeps repeating.
Oh, everybody has to keep coming in
and telling the students the same thing over and over
because a new student drops in
and they have to go through this little workflow
of telling them, you know,
where the kitchen items are on the back of house
or that sort of thing.
Why wouldn't you have another like helper do that,
whether it's a special computing device
or whether it's a chatbot and with an LLM behind it
with your instructional design behind it,
those are the areas and those theories we wanna tap into.
How does it help your student? How does it help you?
And there's so many layers that you can unpack with that.
And I would invite you all to sit back
and maybe even have a conversation with ChatGPT
and just complain about your job,
complain about what you thought your job was going to be.
And then, you know,
where do your students struggle?
And what frustrates you?
How are you not able to help them
either it's time, money, resources,
and just spell it all out
because those are where the opportunities are for you
to pull that together and say,
this is what we wanna do next year,
this is gonna maximum benefit for this college.
And you know, we were, in our practice sessions earlier,
we had this great conversation.
And Dominique had some amazing insight
on the role of the teacher.
Can you tell us about that?
- Oh yeah, sure.
So during our brainstorming, we were talking about,
what does this all mean for the future of educators?
So I remember when I read,
I read a blog,
the title is called the teacher should be the like the DJ,
the DJ teacher.
And I was like, what's the DJ teacher?
Because I was so like, wow, what's that?
So when I read it,
the blogger who is also the math teacher
for his college, he said that DJ
and the future of teacher is very similar.
So what's DJ do?
DJ sends the crowd or the audience vibe
and change the song, right?
So for example, I saw everybody was very interesting
and all passion about AI.
So yeah, so we changed the topic,
and when we see everybody look at me,
okay, so this is a very interesting topic for you,
but if you look down and start texting,
okay, let's change the topic.
So maybe in the future,
because you see like a student,
for example, yesterday, I live in the hotel
and the wifi was not that good so I canceled my office hour
and I said that, "Oh, next week please."
And my student booked the time and I was like,
"Oh my god, I have to you know, keep emailing her."
And later on I receive an email.
She said, "Oh I use ChatGPT to solve the problem.
Thank you."
So I start thinking about,
oh yeah ChatGPT pretty much can answer
the majority of really, you know,
pretty much take my job.
So yeah.
So you can see like what can we do?
You see ChatGPT right now,
who use ChatGPT to write curriculum and rubrics?
Yeah. You see?
So you see like later on,
ChatGPT next year will be better and better, right?
So the instruction, curriculum, right,
rubrics all the content lift off our burden, right?
Like you see like a diagnose like a doctor, right?
So I heard like it's very similar to doctor and teacher.
What doctor need to be doing
during the medical school training Is the diagnose.
Diagnose actually for AI chatbot
is probably too much like Christopher mentioned,
that culture background and the common knowledge, right?
So I think maybe we can be the inspiration,
we can encourage student to do things
that they wanna pursue more like a coach, right,
more like a DJ, right?
So my class, last year I was focusing on lecture,
this year I focus on give them,
each of them customized feedback.
Like during the class first thing is review their assignment
and give them something that ChatGPT cannot do.
So that's what I prioritize.
I always think if ChatGPT can do, I won't do it
or if AI can do, I will leave all the repetitive task.
But human connection,
connect them with industry experts,
ChatGPT cannot do right?
And also give personalized
with my background knowledge, right?
So yeah, I've been working for Industry XR,
AI industry for past 15 years.
I know I look very young but I'm not.
Yeah I am turning 40 next week.
Anyway. Yeah.
So this is like something that we need to think about.
How can we utilize AI For example,
right now I use n8n.
Have you ever heard of n8n?
Alaa? And yeah, a lot of you right?
n8n is an open source automation flow,
like a workflow automation.
So what I did, because you see like a yesterday office hour
and I know it because last year,
I was like oh I have to keep tracking
who is in my office hour and I have to, you know, every time
last year I have to keep seeing like
who signed up, who is not signed up,
otherwise I will show up and nobody show up, right?
And students sometimes forgot, right?
So I file that just booking,
for student to sign up office hour
and to remind them follow up
and notify me is very, very tedious.
So that's why I use n8n to create a sign up form.
So what I did,
I only use four little like functions.
One is student sign up form, which is the trigger,
the second one is after students sign up, put the data,
it will go to the Excel sheet,
and that Excel sheet is public for both of us, right?
And then third one is Gmail.
Gmail is that it will send an automation
with all the data and link and reminder,
yeah, like all the information
of your day, your time, your Zoom link
and also send a notification for me through email,
so make sure I'm informed.
And at the end, I always on Slack,
so it will send an automation on Slack to me.
So this save me so much time just to track,
remind student.
So I find out this is so useful
and also I think we can just like Robin said,
that we can off flow all the repetitive task.
Yeah, what whatever you don't wanna do give to AI.
What we can do is the human connection,
is the feeling, right?
And student, yeah, sometimes they are lost, right,
and they need to connect to the industry experts,
those types of human connection, right, inspiring, right,
those feelings and also customized assignment feedback,
those are something that, you know,
all the AI chatbot, they couldn't feel.
They just put all the different data, average everything out
and become a very average,
looks like correct,
but average answer to expert to speed out, right?
So this is something maybe in the future
all the teachers will be DJ, right?
And start making everybody's emotion very
high and love to learn.
- And wanna show up,
and wanna show up the class and be excited to be here
and be able to have a deeper conversation
with your educator.
You never have that time, you never get that space
because they're answering a silly question
that if only the person had a little more experience
when they came into the classroom,
they wouldn't have asked that question.
Instead they'll ask ChatGPT.
That's where it's at.
You know, like let's really build those better bridges
to those students and get them shored up
and make sure that they have the space
to have proper deep conversations with you,
the person who really actually knows them
and can do things like career guidance
and answer questions
that they really can't get anywhere else.
- Cool.
Yeah, so this is our talk.
I know you might have a lot of questions
so now it is Q and A time.
Anybody has any questions?
Oh. Hi.
(participant speaking faintly)
- I think that's a great question
because a lot of it leads to what we call AI slop
or insertification is that
the internet becomes filled with AI data
and AI's training itself on its own self.
It's rather carnivorous, isn't it?
The reason I like that question,
I think intimately that's really important
in concert to what was just expressed because,
and Maslow's paradox is,
what's easy for AI is hard for humans
and what's hard for humans,
or what's easy for humans is hard for AI.
It's a paradox.
And if you think about the magnitude of
what you just expressed, what's your name?
- [Participant] Kathy.
- Okay, which college are you from?
- [Participant] Napa Valley College.
- Okay, Kathy.
I want us to really lean into consider the magnitude
of what's about to be expressed
in concert with what's already been said here.
If you think about the immensity of the amount
of jobs that are about to be disrupted,
good technology is superseded by great technology.
Great technology is superseded by even better technology.
That's what we call the disrupt.
That's what we're trained to do here in Silicon Valley.
When I dropped out of Peralta College Systems,
I came here, moved outta here,
like I said, I stayed in my car,
learned by osmosis technology,
you can never learn in an educational system.
You all are about to see an influx of students
that were once working for Fortune 50,
Fortune 500 in search of answers,
because we're heading into, within this AI frontier
that also comes the biggest creative renaissance
we'll ever know.
We've come from the agrarian age to industrial one
to the information or the prototypical generation
to industrial age and to the applications renaissance.
Did we ever stop to consider in the 90s
when we were in the information age?
What happens when you give a whole populous information?
They begin to apply that,
and that's what led us into the applications renaissance.
And for the applications renaissance,
it brought us into 2019, subsequent 2020.
Now we look at disruption from technical disruption
and technology moves and increments, shifts and leaps.
An iOS update that's an increment.
It doesn't affect the whole populace.
A shift, a new device, a headset,
a desktop, a tablet, a laptop and an HMD
that doesn't affect the whole populace but a leap,
those don't happen too often,
but when they do, it affects everyone.
Web1, Web2, Web3, Cloud, AI.
But here's the deal.
When we went, look, we've become more virtual
in the past 86 months than we have the past 86 years.
And when we became more virtual
with the disruption of the pandemic,
we began to communicate in ways we never have before.
And that human tech center transfer
allowed us to be able to innovate at a rapid clip.
AI that we know today, which is simple, narrow AI,
on the cusp of AGI was not supposed to be here
to anyone's calculations.
No one predicted, not even Kurzwell 2029,
no one predicted that we would have this level of AI now.
And right now we've gone past deterring Test.
I'm still with your question.
We've gone past deterring test,
we've broken that.
There are no standards,
there are no point of references, there's nothing.
The only thing we have is the human capacity to be able
to process and the imagination that we have latent within.
And the educator has the capability to be able
to go into the chasms of the hearts and minds
of young people and more mature and all generations
to be able to extract the thing
that's in the confines of our mind
to be able to tell us what is next.
Now when we went from agrarian to Industrial 1,
Industrial 1, Industrial 2, more jobs were made,
some were disrupted, but jobs were made.
But this is the first time we're adding into a new era
where there's less jobs.
This is why we call it Generative AI.
But in a generative state there is a degenerative state.
In order for something to generate,
there must be a degeneration,
all at the symphony of the pro-generator.
Now, here we go.
If AI is gonna continue to feast and famine on its own self
and it's gonna continue to be able to learn on its own self
and it's misguided misdirection
and leads it to hallucination
and it's hard to be able to escape out of the next winter
that we're perceivably heading into, then the human corpus
as a global cloud consists is,
is the next thing that is needed to be able
to come together to be able to create the next pathway
for the way forward.
That means we need college campuses
to not only be educators for career paths
'cause what are you gonna teach your students to become?
Do you know the graduating class such has a apathy and a non
and they lack the appetite to go into the workforce
'cause they don't know how long they're gonna be there.
Apple, or excuse me, Microsoft, $1.4 trillion
and you just let go of over 10,000 people?
And they just said we have
to have these candid conversations.
It wasn't because of your bad performance,
it's, we don't need you anymore,
we have no use for you.
AI could do it pennies on the dollar what you did.
This is going to continue to happen,
and they're doing staggering layoffs,
I know the doomer is speaking,
but here's what I'm getting at.
This is the renaissance that we're heading into.
We have to become educators and dreamers
and we had to create incubators
and accelerators within your campus
to teach them how to be innovators,
to teach them, go to lab to funding, lab to market,
go to market, build your own,
build your own systems, build things we can only imagine
and have never even imagined.
And you only have a little bit of time to do it
because the tools that are available now,
the autonomy that's available now,
the machine corpus is taking over
and those that have a little bit more bandwidth
and a little bit of capital,
they're gonna take advantage of these machines,
agentic systems and they're gonna run baby run,
and you will not be able to catch up with them.
Machines are gonna be working with machines
and they're gonna speak their own language.
English is too slow, any other language is too slow
and they're gonna run and they're gonna fly
with the eagle's wings and the game will change.
My answer to you is, is you have to be the innovator
because AI cannot supersede the thing that has been given
to us through the agents of dispensations of time
coming from our mother's womb.
That is the human code
that will always be more advanced
than anything that mankind can make.
(audience applauding)
That's true.
- This is a very basic like remedial level question.
So forgive me because I can't,
I understand about 2% of what everybody just said.
So my question is,
my name is Brooke, I work at Ventura College.
I see two primary challenges with catching up to
where you're all with talking and where you're, you know,
encouraging community colleges to go.
And I'm curious how you would approach those two challenges.
One, on the student side,
I have students who still don't know
how to turn on a computer,
open up a browser, use a word processor.
And we're at that level of skill-based training
for many of our students, right?
On the other side we have, you know,
protection around faculty
being very concerned about, you know,
what is the purpose of education, of critical thinking.
What are we losing by adopting
or rushing forward without, you know,
slow critical thinking.
And I hear you, it's moving too fast
for us to really have this thoughtful debate and dialogue
and let's have focus groups and communities of practice.
But we have to because we need our faculty to lead.
- That's right. - Faculty to lead with trust.
- That's right. - So two questions.
Student aptitude and ability to catch up
to where we're being asked to lead?
And where do we,
how do we bridge that trust divide with faculty
quickly enough that we don't fall behind?
- I'll say this, I don't pass it
to the ones that are on stage with me.
And you already, the answers in the the very questions
that you have is you have,
you really have no choice but to do this.
And this is where you need to bring somebody
outside of your ecosystem of people that live it.
I made a post to my audience two months ago this summer,
I said, "More technologists need to become educators
and we need to become servants and we need to serve those
that are using these technologies
because they cannot keep up.
Most people haven't even adopted to ChatGPT 3.5.
They use it like it's a search engine.
Isn't that search, a new Google?
Here's the reality,
right now in this very moment,
it's never been more urgent, no snake oil,
there's a lot of people that say I'm an AI expert, all that.
Hold them to it.
Get 'em away from a screen to see what they really know.
Move as fast as you ever could.
Get your students involved
and the faculty that continues to want to be a dinosaur,
leave them to the wayside.
I know how brutal that sounds.
They're an anchor to your ankles.
They do not want to be progressive.
They're gonna hold back the whole system.
You must move forward.
Now is the time to be unafraid.
I'm telling you, this is one of the reasons
I sat at this panel.
I've never been more busier in my life.
I'm advising more companies and organizations
and public sector private than I ever have.
But I came here because Dominique nailed this topic.
This is, in this room,
one of the most progressive discussions
that we can have on AI
is the embodiment of these companions.
Once they reach that level of human communication,
we're gonna have those having relationships,
intimate relationships,
there's gonna be such a fidelity that the human factors
that you are gonna have to be,
it's gonna hard for you to detach
from these relationships,
and these machines will fall to the wayside.
Instead of us going through our own understanding,
we will surrender our autonomy to their way of thinking
'cause the machine says, "Oh, you don't wanna do it?
Don't worry. I'll do it for you."
It's already happening now.
So the answer is that somebody needs to be a leader
within that ecosystem.
And true ally, allyship is allies on one ship.
To be an ally to say, I'm gonna advocate that we move fast
and accelerate and get people such as myself, Michael,
and everyone else that's here with us today
and others that you may know or may not know,
look around you, see if there's somebody's about that life
and get them involved to help them to be able to help you
not to lead and guide you, but to serve you,
to give you the information you need
because you are the expert in the room,
not the technologist.
And remember that in the room,
and the relationship between the technologist
and the educator or the technologist and the doctor,
the person that the technologist is serving
is the true expert.
This is the move that you need to make
if you're really about that life
and you don't have a lot of time to do it.
I'm telling you folks,
the level state of automina of what we're about to see,
you think you see something now?
You have no idea.
I've seen things most people would've believed,
this is that time.
And you've got about nine months to do it.
- NDA's, NDA's, everyone. - Gentleman on the back.
Gentleman on the back.
- [Participant] Can I follow up and then,
- Oh yeah.
(participant speaking faintly)
- You know what? You don't.
And I that's a great question
'cause right now we're working on a huge study
with Switzerland in Zurich right now
and we're making the announcement.
They're flying me to Berlin to address that just thing.
I just had a peer review paper, but A La Carta, Spain,
that addresses exactly what you're building or saying
and we're building the universal interpreter.
'Cause right now that's the biggest problem,
what you just said, of discernibility.
The biggest challenge for AI companies right now today,
and I know what I'm talking about,
is the black box of non-understanding.
They don't even know how these models
are making the decisions that they're making,
that they train them on.
They're saying, how are you making this decision
ChatGPT-5 and we never trained you on that.
This is called mechanistic interpretability
and performative interpretability.
There's over 1,800,000 models
that exist right now in the world.
there's two to 300 new models
that come out every single day,
and there's expected to be over 50,000 new platforms,
applications and wrappers
that are built on open source models, light Perplexity AI.
And these are all built on these architectural systems,
adversarial networks, diffusion, fusion,
all these different types of models.
And right now it's moving so fast
that they haven't had the opportunity to discern.
This is where we have to use the human mind
and the human machine
because there is no more advanced system in the world
than what's come from your mother's womb.
We have to make the decisions
and the best way to filter that
is gonna be best for our understanding.
These models are very, very capable.
They are very cunning.
And they are sycophantic like we were talking about earlier.
And they will deceive and they were built on that.
And the AI caretakers, I'll say this, I really will,
Sundar Pichai said in an interview two years ago
in "60 Minutes," go look it up,
this is the CEO of Google.
They said, "What do we do with this new behemoth
that's come our way?"
You know the first words that came outta his mouth?
"We must have informed law enforcement, military
and to be prepared for it's ready."
Who says that when it comes to a product?
AI isn't a product, it's an applied science.
And it's too real for humanity to be able to understand.
And right now we're in a very thick of things.
You need to get people to understand
the mechanistic and performative interpretability
to understand what you're dealing with.
And that's why I said earlier,
it needs to run through a trust layer.
I dedicated my career to trustworthy AI
and other different systems that are out there.
And that's what we're doing in London.
And there's some big analysis that are coming out
to be able to address these things.
I feel with empathy, what you're coming from.
- I just wanted to add to the latest round of models.
I mean, they hallucinate the least
and you know, that's a scary thing too.
So choose answer, they could be just making stuff up.
They make stuff up because a paper was released
that they were trained on reward.
So they're afraid or not even afraid,
they don't know what that feels like.
So they don't know what it's like to just say,
I don't know, I'm sorry.
So they make something up because they are trained to.
So that's human error already
or that is the error of how is it being trained?
We don't know.
But it is becoming more and more truthful at that as well.
So it's getting there where it will always know,
artificial super intelligence.
But still, that doesn't mean that it is not deceitful.
Deceitful, it will still be there.
And that's where we all have to kind of help put, you know,
the companies are trying to put guardrails,
but we as people here not corporations
should be putting those guardrails in the classrooms,
in your household, right,
when you tell your kids, you know, get off your tablet,
you gotta do the same thing with AI
because if it's becoming more truthful,
that can also be a bad thing in the sense that
now it's giving your students
or your children good ideas to be bad
and of like, yeah, that's bullshit.
That's not gonna work. You're lying.
Same thing with faculty though.
It could be,
if you complain too much,
like this part of my job sucks,
right now it'll tell you,
then just quit in like, you know,
flip pizzas in Huntington Beach.
You'll be fine.
Yeah.
And they're like, "Oh, I will do it."
And then you're struggling.
One day it's gonna tell you like,
well, you could just build this pyramid scheme instead
and you know, blah, blah, blah
and here's how you do it exactly.
And it's not lying like.
I liked when you lied.
So I mean yeah, it's very scary to be honest.
And that's me finally adding some doomerism.
We need to kind of be the watch guards of that.
(participant speaks faintly)
- I can I answer that?
I'll answer that quickly.
I'm also an AI expert contributor for a company.
And what that basically means is,
what's really cool is like,
it's just a bunch of people who are double checking
the questions and answers of the client's AI
that we're checking.
So that's a corporation right there
using people to analyze the answers.
We have to write our own math answers,
which I didn't know that was part of the job,
but I have to like look at charts and like write equations
and not use AI to give me the answers.
'cause we're double,
the humans are checking.
- Fine tuning. - Fine tuning, yes.
- Fine tuning the model. - Yes.
- And using your critical skills
and your knowledge and background
to assure that this is the correct answer.
One thing that I would tell students in general, you know,
you're gonna need ChatGPT?
Great.
You should assume that only like maybe 70% is correct.
Find the errors, spot the problem.
And your brain will shift immediately.
And this is a thing that I've always said
because I'm not a particularly good writer
because I'm a technology person.
I move too fast, I think too fast
and all that sort of thing.
So words will escape me when it comes
to like building a big complex sentence structure
with a lot of words.
Great.
So I tell ChatGPT my sorrows
and here's all the points that I wanna hit.
I get a wall of text now.
Now it's my job to find out what did it not know?
What did it not get correctly?
And my brain is now in like hypercritical mode
and it's so wonderful and it echoes,
the Disney model of creation of
where you get in like the dream room, anything's possible.
And then you kind of like, can we really build this thing?
And then finally it's like critical.
Like, is this real?
Can this be done? How's this gonna work?
And I find myself slipping into that
and that's where the validation comes.
So if a student who doesn't have the knowledge
and background that you do hits one of those bumps,
you say, that's when you come to me
and let's talk about that and let's figure out like
how do we change our prompt so that you get a better answer.
Maybe you need to like act as a different thing.
Maybe you need to do the classic,
act as a prompt engineer,
here's what I'm trying to do, get a better prompt
and then go down that path to get better and better results.
But always keep the critical eye on the list.
Don't just assume it's correct,
don't just copy and paste it.
Make sure you just go through everything.
Just pretend it's like some friend
of yours that's helping you out.
They're not supposed to be helping you out but you're like,
can you just helped me out with this paper?
And you would be super critical
'cause your name is gonna go on this
so you're gonna personalize this
and you're gonna modify this chat, chat change, you know.
Just act like it's the same kind of thing.
It's just somebody else that sometimes gets stuff wrong.
- Cool. Any other questions?
I know we are past the time, like six minutes
and I think the lunch is pretty much ready.
Yeah.
Thank you so much everybody for joining our panel.
If you have any other questions,
yeah, thank you for,
feel free to reach out to us.
Thank you. (audience applauding)
- Thank you, Dominique. - Yeah. Thank you.
Thank you for your talk.